All right, so this is CS50.
欢迎来到 CS50。
My name is David Malan, and this is Harvard University's Introduction to the Intellectual Enterprises of Computer Science and the Art of Programming.
我叫 David Malan，这是哈佛大学的「计算机科学导论与编程艺术」课程。
And this, of course, is our special family weekend, wherein not only are CS50's own students here in the audience, but also some family members as well.
当然，这是我们特殊的家庭周末，不仅 CS50 的学生在现场，还有一些家庭成员也来了。
Now, you're showing up in the semester a little bit late.
现在，你们在这个学期来稍微晚了一些。
We've just tackled week eight, which is really our ninth week since computer scientists start counting from zero.
我们刚刚结束了第八周的课程，实际上是第九周，因为计算机科学家从 0 开始计数。
So we've done a whole lot of work over the past few weeks, as you might have heard via emails or text messages home, including a language known here as binary.
所以在过去的几周里，我们做了很多工作，就像你们可能通过电子邮件或短信在家听说的那样，包括一种叫做二进制的语言。
So on the screen here, of course, is a lot of 0's and 1's.
所以屏幕上有很多 0 和 1。
And suffice it to say, let me sum up the past nine weeks with, this is what's going on underneath the hood.
简单来说，让我用一句话概括过去九周的内容，这就是底层发生的事情。
But of course, today, we thought we'd make things a little more accessible, a little more broadly applicable.
当然，今天，我们想让事情更容易理解，更广泛地应用。
And indeed, our focus today will not be on what these patterns of 0's and 1's represent.
事实上，我们今天的重点将不是这些 0 和 1 的模式代表什么。
Which, in astute eye, might notice are replicated visually with these light bulbs being in a pattern on and off.
敏锐的眼睛可能会注意到，这些灯泡以亮和灭的模式在视觉上复制了这些内容。
And as your child might have hinted before class or perhaps now, this might very well spell a word up to eight characters long.
正如你的孩子在上课前或现在可能暗示的那样，这很可能拼出一个最多八个字符的单词。
Because you can encode, even in the real world, things digital too. But today, we'll focus on things much more high level, this notion of cybersecurity, like the security of our data,
因为即使在现实世界中，你也可以对事物进行数字编码。但今天，我们将专注于更高级别的东西，即网络安全这个概念，比如我们数据的安全，
our privacy of our systems, particularly on the internet nowadays, because presumably all of us are carrying technologies around in our pocket, using laptops and desktops every day.
我们系统的隐私，尤其是在当今的互联网上，因为我们每个人大概都在口袋里装着各种技术设备，每天都在使用笔记本电脑和台式机。
And so the goal today is to not stipulate that this is what's going on underneath the hood, but let's solve some problems at a higher level
所以今天我们的目标不是规定引擎盖下面正在发生的事情，而是让我们在更高的层次上解决一些问题，这样当你回到你所访问的地方时，
so that your homework, when you go back to wherever you're visiting from, can actually be to apply some of today's lessons learned. So with that said, perhaps the most common familiar defense Of one's systems and data, phone and laptops and desktops would just be these simple passwords.
你的家庭作业实际上就可以应用今天学到的课程。
因此，话虽如此，也许最常见的保护个人系统和数据的防御手段，比如手机、笔记本电脑和台式机，就是这些简单的密码。
Unfortunately, you and I are, frankly, as humans, not all that good at choosing passwords.
不幸的是，坦率地说，你和我都不是那么擅长选择密码。
And this is, in itself, a relatively weak form of defense, even though each of us has dozens, hundreds of passwords nowadays, or at least dozens or hundreds of accounts, maybe. Fives or tens of dozens of passwords.
这本身就是一种相对薄弱的防御形式，即使我们每个人现在都有几十个、几百个密码，或者至少是几十个或几百个账户，也许是五六十个密码。
Indeed, if you're in the habit of reusing passwords, we'll see today probably among our first lessons learned.
事实上，如果你有重复使用密码的习惯，我们今天可能会从我们的第一个教训中学到。
So for instance, if we look back at the past year, 2021, thanks to security researchers who take a look at data that has been hacked or leaked online by way of public databases, we have a sense, as computer scientists,
例如，如果我们回顾过去的一年，2021 年，多亏了安全研究人员查看了通过公共数据库在线泄露或被黑客入侵的数据，作为计算机科学家，
我们了解到最流行的或者等价地，看看你我都为系统选择的那些最糟糕的密码是什么。
of what the most popular or equivalently, what some of the worst passwords are that you and I are choosing for our system.
So as of this past year, according to one measure, the most commonly used password in systems everywhere was 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
根据一项指标，截至去年，各地系统中最常用的密码是 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6。
All right, number two password in our top 10 here list was only slightly longer, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
好吧，我们前十名中的第二名密码只是稍微长一点，1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9。
After that, we took a turn in the other direction, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 alone.
在那之后，我们转向了另一个方向，仅仅是 1, 2, 3, 4, 5。
After that, got a little more interesting, QWERTY, which might sound pretty cryptic, but not if you look down at your US keyboard, and it's the top left-hand row of the keys on an American keyboard.
在那之后，变得更有趣了一些，QWERTY，这听起来可能很神秘，但如果你低头看看你的美式键盘，它就是美式键盘上左上角的那排键。
So also, not all that hard.
也不难猜到。
Perhaps not surprisingly, a little disconcertingly, number five was Password.
也许并不奇怪，但有点令人不安的是，第五名是 Password。
Meanwhile, number 6 returns us to digits. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
同时，第六名又回到了数字。1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8。
After that, really less effort. 1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1.
在那之后，真的更不用费力了。1, 1, 1, 1, 1, 1。
After that, a little more variation, but not all that much. 1, 2, 3, 1, 2, 3.
在那之后，稍微多了一点变化，但也没有那么多。1, 2, 3, 1, 2, 3。
After that, it's getting even less interesting. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 0.
在那之后，它变得越来越没意思了。1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 0。
And then lastly, topping the list is just 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
最后，排在榜首的是 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7。
So this is not a good top 10 list to be on.
所以这不是一个你想上的“十大”榜单。
So among today's first takeaways is if you see your password on this screen, you didn't make the list in a good way.
所以今天的第一条重要信息是，如果你在这个屏幕上看到了你的密码，那么你上榜的方式可不怎么样。
This means hundreds, thousands, millions of other people probably have that password of yours.
这意味着可能有成百上千，甚至数百万人都在使用你的密码。
Now, in and of itself, that's not necessarily worrisome, because I don't know who has these passwords in a room as large as this.
现在，就其本身而言，这并不一定令人担忧，因为我不知道在这个房间里谁有这些密码。
But just intuitively, why is this a bad thing?
但凭直觉，为什么这是件坏事？
Either parent or child, welcome to raise a hand here.
家长或孩子，欢迎举手示意。
Why might this be?
为什么会这样呢？
Intuitively, yeah.
凭直觉，是的。
So access to it.
可以访问它。
I mean, we literally, as computer scientists now, have a database of really common passwords.
作为计算机科学家，我们确实拥有一个包含常见密码的数据库。
And your thoughts?
你有什么想法？
Yeah, you can just find it out quickly.
可以快速找到它。
I mean, you could imagine trying to guess someone's password by just typing in random letters, random numbers, random words.
你可以想象一下，尝试随机输入字母、数字和单词来猜别人的密码。
But not if you have a top 10 list. Like, the adversaries in the world might as well just start with this list.
但如果你有排名前十的列表，情况就不同了，世界上的攻击者们很可能就是从这份列表开始的。
Now, you'll notice that even absent from this are slight variants.
你会注意到，即使在这份列表中也没有细微的变体。
Like, some of you might be thinking, I'm not on the list because I do something clever, like I use an exclamation point for the number 1.
有些人可能会想，我使用感叹号代替数字1，我的密码不在列表中。
or a 3 for an E or a 5 for an S. And based on the smiles in the room right now, you're not all that clever, it turns out, because other people are smiling too,
或者用3代替E，用5代替S。从现在房间里大家的笑容来看，你们并没有那么聪明，因为其他人也在笑，
which is to say that an adversary can take those same heuristics that you might think are making things more secure by just tweaking some letters to numbers or vice versa.
这意味着攻击者可以使用相同的策略，通过将某些字母调整为数字，反之亦然，你可能认为这样做会让密码更安全。
But if you're doing it and other people are doing it, the bad guys, so to speak, are going to be doing it as well.
但如果你这样做，其他人也这样做，那么所谓的坏人也会这样做。
So unfortunately, when it comes to passwords, Better is longer and random and really unguessable, but that's not what most of us have.
不幸的是，说到密码，越长、越随机、越难猜越好，但这并不是我们大多数人的做法。
In fact, case in point, on our phones, whether you have an Android device or an iPhone nowadays, odds are you have something relatively simplistic protecting it, if you have anything at all.
事实上，举个例子，在我们的手机上，无论你是用Android设备还是iPhone，如果你设置了密码保护，那很可能是一个相对简单的密码。
But at least Apple and Google are pretty good at at least nudging us to choose these kinds of passcodes now.
但至少苹果和谷歌现在很擅长引导我们选择这类密码。
And a four-digit passcode is quite common nowadays.
四位数密码现在很常见。
And so here's where we have an opportunity, thanks to the URL that you saw on the screen earlier, to conjecture as a group Just how long might it take an adversary, someone out there who's out to get us or get one of us, how long might it take an adversary to figure out your phone's four-digit passcode?
因此，我们可以利用之前屏幕上显示的URL，作为一个小组来推测，攻击者需要多长时间才能破解你的四位数手机密码？
This is CS50's own Carter. Carter, if we could switch over and poll the audience here.
这位是CS50的Carter。Carter，我们可以切换画面并对观众进行投票。
If you take out your phone or laptop, whatever device you might have used a few minutes ago to scan that QR code or to visit that same URL,
请拿出你的手机或笔记本电脑，用你几分钟前扫描二维码或访问相同URL的设备。
You can see these questions on your browser.
你可以在浏览器上看到这些问题。
And if you can't, that's fine.
如果你看不到，也没关系。
We'll share some aggregate data nonetheless.
我们会分享一些汇总数据。
But you should have an opportunity to tap one of your answers.
你可以选择你认为对的答案。
And we'll give folks a few more seconds if you'd like to play along at home.
如果你想一起参与，我们会给大家多几秒钟的时间。
And here in just a moment.
稍等片刻。
Probably have many people reporting, but why don't we go ahead and take a look at some percentages.
可能很多人都在回答，我们不妨来看看比例。
It looks like most of you, 67% are proposing just a few seconds.
看起来大多数人，67% 的人认为是几秒钟。
So that's not all that good news if it's a four-digit passcode.
如果是一个四位数的密码，这可不是什么好消息。
Some of you are hoping it's a few minutes.
有些人希望是几分钟。
8% are hoping a few hours. More than 4% of you are really hoping perhaps it's a few days.
8% 的人希望是几个小时。超过 4% 的人真的希望可能是几天。
Well, let's actually consider how we can answer this question and make today not just conceptual, but a little quantitative, too, and see if we can't slap some numbers on questions like these.
让我们实际考虑一下如何回答这个问题，并使今天不仅是概念性的，而且还有一点量化的内容，看看我们是否可以对这类问题进行一些数字上的量化。
So ultimately, you can make more informed decisions with your system security.
这样，你就可以在你的系统安全方面做出更明智的决定。
So for instance, when it comes to four-digit passcodes, rather than just consider How secure it is, well, let's make it a more precise question.
例如，当涉及到四位数密码时，与其只考虑它的安全性，不如把它变成一个更精确的问题。
Like, what are the forms of attack? Well, the simplest attack might be just someone grabbing your phone, be it in your family or maybe at Starbucks or the airport or the like, and just starting all possible combinations.
比如，攻击的形式有哪些？最简单的攻击方式可能是有人拿着你的手机，
无论是在你的家里，还是在星巴克、机场或类似的地方，然后开始尝试所有可能的组合。
Maybe 0, 0, 0, 0, then 0, 0, 0, 1, and 0, 0, 0, 2. We could maybe automate this a little bit.
也许是 0, 0, 0, 0，然后是 0, 0, 0, 1，然后是 0, 0, 0, 2。也许我们可以把这个过程自动化一点。
So for instance, I might potentially be able to do something like roboticize this here.
例如，我可能可以用机器人来完成这个任务。
Let me go ahead and full screen a quick video here.
让我全屏播放一段视频。
That's just going to paint a picture in just a moment on the screen of how, if we're a really clever adversary and know how to build things, well, at least maybe we could automate some of that process.
这将在一瞬间在屏幕上描绘出一幅画面，如果我们是一个非常聪明的对手，并且知道如何构建东西，至少我们可以将其中一些过程自动化。
So here's an Android phone sitting on a counter.
这是一部放在柜台上的安卓手机。
Here's a very simple tripod and a little touch device robotically doing all of that hacking for you.
这是一个非常简单的三脚架和一个小型的触摸设备，可以自动为你完成所有黑客攻击。
Starting at 0, 0, 0, 0, probably all the way up to 9, 9, 9, 9.
从 0, 0, 0, 0 开始，一直到 9, 9, 9, 9。
Now, that, too, wasn't necessarily all that fast.
然而，这也不一定就快。
But at least the adversary can step away and doesn't actually have to be bothered with the time involved, the cost involved in actually hacking that particular device.
但至少攻击者可以抽身离开，不必为实际入侵特定设备所需的时间和成本而烦恼。
Well, let's go one level deeper, a little more interestingly, and consider here.
我们来深入探讨一下，考虑一个更有趣的问题。
How much time, really, this so-called brute force attack would take. And that's actually a term of art.
这种所谓的暴力攻击到底需要多少时间？这实际上是一个专业术语。
Much like in yesteryear, when maybe there was a battering ram trying to brute force their way into a castle or something like that,
就像过去，有人可能用攻城锤试图强行攻入城堡，数字世界的暴力攻击就是有人手动尝试所有可能的密码，
a brute force attack digitally is just someone trying, manually, all possible codes, or maybe robotically trying all possible codes, but generally automating the process in some way to go through all possibilities.
或者用机器人尝试所有可能的密码，但通常会以某种方式自动化这个过程，遍历所有可能性。
Well, if you've got, for instance, A four-digit passcode, let's ask maybe a follow-up question here, not how long it will take, but how many possible four-digit passcodes are there?
假设你有一个四位数的密码，我们先不问需要多长时间，而是问有多少种可能的四位数密码？
Because then maybe we can do some quick math.
因为也许我们可以快速计算一下。
And if every passcode takes me a second or a few milliseconds or the like, then I think we can try to extrapolate from that whether the first answer was seconds or minutes or days or hours or something else.
如果每个密码需要我花费一秒或几毫秒，那么我认为我们可以由此推断出第一个答案是几秒、几分钟、几天、几小时还是其他什么。
How many four-digit passcodes are possible?
四位数密码有多少种可能？
If you take out your same device, it should have just changed automatically.
拿出你的设备，它应该已经自动更新了。
If it doesn't seem to have, maybe reload your browser with some menu option.
如果看起来没有更新，也许可以用菜单选项刷新浏览器。
And then tap in here.
然后点击这里。
How many four-digit passcodes are possible?
四位数密码有多少种可能？
4 total, 40, 9,999, 10,000, or unsure is OK, too.
总共 4 个，40 个，9,999 个，10,000 个，或者不确定也可以。
So let's see. We'll give you a few more moments.
我们再给大家一些时间。
How many four-digit passcodes are possible?
四位数密码有多少种可能？
And shall we reveal the results?
我们来揭晓答案吧？
So now it looks like a few of you, 2% of you, are saying just four passcodes, 40, 9,999.
现在看来，你们中的一些人，2% 的人说是只有 4 个密码，40 个，9,999 个。
There's definitely some contention here, and 6% are unsure.
这里肯定存在一些争议，6% 的人不确定。
Well, how do we wrap our minds around this?
我们该如何理解这个问题？
Well, let's just kind of do this real simply here.
我们来简单地分析一下。
Let me switch back over to doing a bit of math, and if we have here 10 possibilities for each digit.
我们回到数学上来，如果每一位数字都有 10 种可能性。
If there's four digits, each digit can be 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
如果总共是四位数，那每一位可以是 0、1、2、3、4、5、6、7、8、9。
So that's 10 possibilities.
也就是 10 种可能性。
So if you think about the number of permutations, that's 10 possibilities for the first digit, times 10 for the next, times 10 for the next, times 10 for the next.
所以如果你想想排列组合的数量，第一位是 10 种可能性，乘以第二位的 10 种，再乘以第三位的 10 种，再乘以第四位的 10 种。
And so if we do that out, 10 times 10 times 10 times 10, or 10 to the fourth, there are indeed, as 66% of you found, 10,000 possibilities.
所以如果我们计算一下，10 乘以 10 乘以 10 乘以 10，或者说 10 的四次方，就像你们 66% 的人发现的那样，确实有 10,000 种可能性。
So now we can kind of work backwards and decide, how long is it going to take for an adversary to hack into this phone?
现在我们可以反过来思考，攻击者需要多长时间才能破解这部手机？
Because if it's one attack, one guess per second, well, that's going to map out to 10,000 seconds.
因为如果每秒钟尝试一次，那就需要 10,000 秒。
But maybe not if the adversary isn't a roboticist or a human.
但如果攻击者不是机器人或人类，情况可能就不是这样了。
What if they're, like, a software programmer, someone who's taken even a class introductory like CS50 and learned a little bit of programming?
如果他们是一个软件程序员，一个上过 CS50 之类的入门课程、学过一点编程的人呢？
Well, a little bit frighteningly, it's not all that hard to,
有点可怕的是，这并不难，
Hack into systems if you just know how to code, too, and really have the computer do your work for you.
如果你知道如何编写代码，并且能让计算机帮你完成工作，那么入侵系统并不难。
So in fact, let me go ahead and change over to another screen on my computer here.
让我切换到我电脑上的另一个屏幕。
This is different for students in the group from VS Code.
这对 VS Code 组的学生来说是不一样的。
This is just a black and white version of it that we've used briefly in the past.
这只是我们过去简要使用过的黑白版本。
And I'm just going to go ahead and create a program called crack.py to crack something.
我将创建一个名为 crack.py 的程序来破解一些东西。
Just technically means to figure out what it is, figure out a password in this case.
从技术上讲，这意味着要找出它是什么，在这种情况下就是找出密码。
And .py means I'm going to use a programming language that we here in CS50 have been dabbling in the past couple of weeks, with more to come next week as well.
.py 意味着我将使用一种编程语言，我们在 CS50 过去几周一直在学习这种语言，下周还会继续学习。
So it turns out, and you need not understand each of these lines of code,
事实证明，你不需要理解每一行代码，
If I want to try maybe generating all 10,000 possible codes, I'm not going to bother with a robot.
如果我想尝试生成所有 10,000 个可能的密码，我就不会用机器人了。
I've got all these cables coming out of my computer.
我的电脑上插着这么多线。
And odds are, one of them is a USB cable or a lightning cable.
很有可能其中一根就是 USB 数据线或者 lightning 连接线。
Surely, we could figure out how to connect laptop or desktop to phone and just automate the process nowadays by just sending all of the numbers into the phone until one unlocks the trick, just like in the movies or TV.
当然，我们肯定能找到办法将笔记本电脑或台式机连接到手机上，像电影或电视里那样，将所有数字自动发送到手机上，直到其中一个数字解锁成功。
Well, in Python, I could write a program that does this as follows.
在 Python 中，我可以编写一个程序来实现这一点。
I can import, so to speak, all of the decimal digits, 0 through 9.
我可以导入，也可以说是导入从 0 到 9 的所有十进制数字。
And this, for students in the room, is just a slightly better version of typing out 10 different numbers manually.
对于在座的学生来说，这只是比手动输入 10 个不同的数字稍微好一点的版本。
I can also import from a library, so to speak, called itertools, for iteration tools, which means to do something again and again.
我还可以从一个库中导入，也就是叫做 itertools 的库，表示迭代工具，意思是反复做某件事。
I can import a function. called product, which means the cross product, like combine this with this some number of times. And then it's just two more lines of code.
我可以导入一个叫做 product 的函数，意思是叉积，就像把这个和这个组合多次一样。然后就只剩下两行代码了。
I can use what's called a loop in programming.
我可以使用编程中称为循环的东西。
So for every passcode in the cross product of all 10 of those digits repeated a total of four times, let me go ahead and, rather than bother connecting my phone and hacking my own phone, let me just print out every one of those 10,000 codes on the screen.
所以对于所有 10 个数字重复四次的叉积中的每一个密码，
与其费心连接我的手机并破解我自己的手机，不如让我直接在屏幕上打印出这 10,000 个密码中的每一个。
And we'll see how fast the hacker could do this.
然后我们会看看黑客能多快完成。
Let me go ahead and print, and with an asterisk, which is a little trick to format it nicely, I'm going to print out each of those passcodes.
让我来打印，用星号，这是一个格式化的小技巧，我会打印出每个密码。
And that's it.
就是这样。
Four lines of code, maybe 40 seconds of talking, but maybe really four seconds of coding if I actually did this without the audience.
四行代码，可能说了 40 秒，但如果我真的在没有观众的情况下这样做，可能只需要 4 秒钟的编码时间。
And now let me go ahead and save the file.
现在让我来保存文件。
And I'm going to run, as we do every day in class of late, Python of crack.py.
我要运行，就像我们最近每天在课堂上做的那样，运行 Python crack.py。
And when I hit Enter, I should see on the screen all 10,000 possibilities from 0, 0, 0, 0 to 9, 9, 9, 9.
当我按下回车键时，我应该在屏幕上看到从 0, 0, 0, 0 到 9, 9, 9, 9 的所有 10,000 种可能性。
So let's see. Is it a few seconds, minutes, hours, or? Days.
让我们看看，是几秒、几分钟、几小时，还是？ 几天。
Done.
完成了。
So barely even seconds, plural, if that.
所以连几秒钟都不到，复数形式。
So that should be a little disconcerting, because all that adversary needs to do is grab your phone off the counter, plug in a cable, and boom, they're done.
这有点让人担忧，因为攻击者只需要从桌子上拿起你的手机，插上一根线，瞬间就能成功。
There's no ticking clock or worries, as in the movies or TV, that maybe you're going to come into the room.
不像电影或电视里那样，你需要担心时间不够用，或者你会突然走进房间。
You don't need that much of a window of time.
你不需要那么长的破解时间。
What would be better than this?
有什么比这更好的方法吗？
Well, let's consider what our options might be if we don't want to just use four-digit passcodes.
如果我们不想只使用四位数的密码，可以考虑哪些选择呢？
Some of you, indeed, might have better passcodes than that.
实际上，你们中的一些人可能设置了比这更好的密码。
And maybe you use four-letter passcodes instead.
也许你使用的是四位字母的密码。
So A through Z, maybe uppercase and lowercase.
比如 A 到 Z，也许还区分大小写。
That starts to make things a little more interesting.
这就开始变得有趣了。
So should we pull this question, too?
那我们也来算算这个吧？
If we upgrade from four digits to just four letters, English letters, A through Z, uppercase and lowercase, why don't we go ahead and pull the group here and ask, how many four-letter passcodes are there instead?
如果我们把四位数字密码升级为四位字母密码，也就是 A 到 Z 的英文字母，区分大小写，那么总共有多少种可能的四位字母密码呢？
So this time, the range starts at four.
这一次，范围从 4 开始。
Still not the right answer, though, this time.
不过，这次的答案仍然不正确。
How many four-letter passcodes are possible?
有多少种可能的四位字母密码？
Take a couple more seconds.
再给大家一些时间思考。
All right.
好了。
Almost a couple hundred responses in already.
已经收到近 200 个答案了。
Few more seconds.
再给大家几秒钟。
And. Why don't we go ahead and reveal now the answers, which are, OK, so we've solved a couple of problems at least.
然后… 让我们揭晓答案，我们至少解决了一些问题。
So we've, well, OK, someone's just messing with us now.
有人在耍我们。
All right, so it looks like most of you, 76% of you, have claimed it's 7 million plus possibilities.
看起来你们大部分人，76% 的人认为是 700 万种可能性。
So that's encouraging, because that's a whole order of magnitude more than before.
这很令人鼓舞，因为这比以前多了一个数量级。
Well, let's figure out how we might do this mathematically.
我们来看看如何用数学方法计算。
So we've got, 26 lowercase, 26 uppercase, that's 52 possibilities now for each of those four digits.
我们有 26 个小写字母，26 个大写字母，这四位数字每个都有 52 种可能性。
So that's 52 times itself four times, which indeed, either off the top of your head, a good guess, a calculator on the same device you're using right now, indeed gives us 7 million instead.
也就是 52 乘以自身四次，不管你是心算、估算还是用计算器，结果确实是 700 万。
Well, what might be slightly better than that?
还有什么可能比这更好？
Well, maybe four characters.
也许是四个字符。
And this, indeed, is what your Macs, PCs, and phones are urging us to do nowadays.
这确实是现在的 Mac、PC 和手机都在敦促我们做的事情。
Not just numbers, not just letters, but really annoying punctuation.
不仅是数字，不仅是字母，还有烦人的标点符号。
So it really looks cryptic, not just to the adversary, but also to you and me, unfortunately.
所以它看起来很神秘，不仅对对手来说，对我们来说也很难懂。
And that's the downside.
这就是缺点。
But here now, we have a mental model and really a computational framework via which we can evaluate the security of these.
但现在，我们有了一个思维模型和计算框架来评估它们的安全性。
And I'll go ahead and spoil some of the math here if we've got 52, Letters of the alphabet, uppercase and lowercase, 10 digits.
如果我们有 52 个字母，包括大小写，10 个数字，我先把其中的一些数学知识剧透一下。
And if I count them out on my keyboard, about 32 punctuation symbols in typical English grammar.
如果我在键盘上数一下，典型的英语语法中大约有 32 个标点符号。
That actually gives us 94 possibilities now, which is up from 52, which is up from 10.
这实际上给了我们 94 种可能性，高于 52，也高于 10。
So now we're really moving.
现在我们真的在进步了。
And now that would give us 78 million possibilities, so another order of magnitude.
现在这就给了我们 7800 万种可能性，又是一个数量级。
Now, it's still going to be relatively fast, because you know what?
现在，它仍然会相对较快，因为你知道吗？
I can actually do this. Let me go back into my code here.
我实际上可以做到这一点，让我回到我的代码中。
Let me reopen the same program, and I can point out just how easy it is to make these changes.
让我重新打开同一个程序，我可以指出进行这些更改是多么容易。
Instead of importing digits, as before, I can import, as your child might know, ASCII letters, which are A through Z, uppercase, lowercase.
我可以导入 ASCII 字符（而不是像以前那样导入数字），如你的孩子可能知道的那样，ASCII 字符是大写和小写的 A 到 Z。
And I can just change this here.
我可以在这里更改。
ASCII letters.
ASCII 字符。
And so this was that first version where we just changed to letters.
这就是我们更改为字母的第一个版本。
Let me now rerun the code.
现在让我重新运行代码。
And instead of seeing numbers, we'll see letters flying across the screen.
我们将看到字母飞过屏幕，而不是数字。
And if I walk over here to the screen, we'll see that by the time I get here, we're halfway through the entire alphabet lowercase.
如果我走到屏幕这边，我们会看到，当我走到这里时，我们已经完成了一半的小写字母表。
If I now start walking away, I think, yep, we're already done now with uppercase as well.
如果我现在开始走开，我想，是的，我们现在已经完成了大写字母。
If I upgrade this slightly further, let's go ahead and take it one more level and perhaps do Let's say ASCII letters and digits and punctuation.
如果我进一步升级它，让我们更进一步，也许可以这样做，比如 ASCII 字母、数字和标点符号。
And this would be the Pythonic way to say that.
这是 Pythonic 的表达方式。
And I'm going to add to those letters those same digits, those same punctuation symbols.
我要将那些相同的数字、相同的标点符号添加到这些字母中。
Let me shrink my font just so the code still fits on the screen.
让我缩小我的字体，以便代码仍然适合屏幕。
And what we now have is, with two seconds of changes, a program that if I run this version, whoops.
现在我们得到的是，经过两秒钟的更改，如果我运行此版本，程序就会出现问题。
Without the typographical error, this is what we call in CS50 a bug.
没有排版错误，这就是我们在 CS50 中所说的错误。
So now we run the same.
现在我们运行相同的。
This is what we call in CS50 a second bug.
这就是我们在 CS50 中所说的第二个错误。
Punctuation.
标点符号。
OK.
好的。
This is where I cross my fingers.
这就是我祈祷的地方。
OK.
好的。
So now it's going to be a little hard to see as it flies across the screen, but you probably are seeing glimpses of some weird punctuation characters as well.
现在屏幕上滚动太快，可能有点看不清了，但你应该已经瞥见了一些奇怪的标点符号。
And I won't waste our time trying to talk through this, because this is going to take longer.
我就不浪费时间解释这个了，因为这需要很长时间。
We're still in the lowercase.
我们还在小写字母阶段。
I'm still over here already.
我这里还没到 n 呢。
We've not even gotten to n, now o, then p. So this is going to run longer.
我们还没到 n，然后是 o，然后是 p。所以这还需要一段时间。
But let's end with one final question on the security of all these systems.
但最后让我们以一个关于所有这些系统安全性的问题来结束。
I'm going to cancel that by hitting Control-C on my keyboard.
我要按键盘上的 Control-C 来取消。
And let's ask the question instead.
让我们换个问题。
If we use eight-character passwords, so twice as many characters, but even that is not terribly long, right?
如果我们使用八位数密码，也就是两倍于之前的字符数，但这也不算太长，对吧？
This is eight characters alone on the stage.
这只是八个字符。
Eight characters using letters, numbers, and punctuation might be better.
使用字母、数字和标点符号的八个字符可能会更好。
Let's do one final vote here, if we could.
我们来做最后一次投票。
On your same device, how many eight-character possibilities are there now for these passcodes?
在相同的设备上，现在这些八位数密码有多少种可能性？
And now forward and even make the list this time.
现在发送答案，这次还要列出来。
All right, a few more seconds, about 100 responses so far.
再过几秒钟，目前为止大约有 100 个回复。
How about we go ahead and, Carter, if you wouldn't mind, let's reveal the results based on the vote.
Carter，如果你不介意的话，我们继续公布投票结果吧。
A pretty decent spread here, although the quadrillions are quickly buzzing in and they're contending with the others here.
结果分布相当不错，不过 quadrillion 很快就冲上来了，正在和其他选项竞争。
Looks like 44% of you said quintillion.
看来 44% 的人选择了 quintillion。
34% said quadrillion.
34% 的人选择了 quadrillion。
And this time, for the first time, you overbid.
这次你第一次出价过高了。
So indeed, if we go back to the math here, at least the majority overbid.
如果我们回头看这里的数学计算，至少大多数人都出价过高。
If we have eight character passcodes, that gives us 94. Times itself 8 times, or 94 to the 8th power.
如果我们有 8 个字符的密码，那就是 94 乘以自身 8 次，或者说是 94 的 8 次方。
And in fact, that gives us roughly 6 quadrillion, 95 trillion, 689 billion, 385 million, 410,000, and 816 possible passcodes.
实际上，这大约是 6 quadrillion 95 trillion 689 billion 385 million 410,000 零 816 种可能的密码。
Now, what does that mean?
这意味着什么呢？
Well, the adversary's algorithm, the step-by-step code that they write to try to hack into your phone, is no different.
攻击者的算法，也就是他们为入侵你的手机而编写的代码，没什么两样。
And honestly, if your passcode is, Eight characters long, but they're 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0.
说实话，如果你的密码有 8 个字符长，但它们是 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0。
You're no more secure fundamentally.
你的安全程度从根本上来说并没有提高。
You really want to be somewhere in the sweet spot of that massive range of values so that if the adversary tries this brute force attack, just running through all possibilities, they will eventually reach your passcode.
你真正想要的是在那个庞大值域中的某个最佳位置，这样，如果攻击者尝试这种暴力攻击，仅仅是遍历所有可能性，他们最终会找到你的密码。
Just mathematically, it will be there.
从数学上讲，它就在那里。
Hopefully, though, well, maybe not hopefully, you and I and they will be gone from this world, because that much time will have passed.
但愿，也许不是但愿，你、我和他们都将离开这个世界，因为已经过去了那么长时间。
And if we do out the math here, this number of seconds, for instance, is long past when we will no longer be here.
如果我们计算一下，这个秒数，例如，已经远远超过了我们不复存在的时间。
That's the sort of measure is we don't fundamentally change the equation for the adversary.
这种衡量标准是我们没有从根本上改变攻击者的等式。
It's still the same risk.
风险还是一样的。
It's still the same attack.
攻击方式还是一样的。
But you significantly drive down the probability of success on their part.
但你大大降低了他们成功的可能性。
Or conceptually, you drive up the cost to the adversary.
或者从概念上讲，你提高了攻击者的成本。
And indeed, even in the physical world, this is true.
事实上，即使在现实世界中也是如此。
You just want your passcode in the digital world really to be better than someone else's.
你只是希望你在数字世界中的密码真的比别人的好。
Because you want someone else's passcode to be the one that the adversary does something with.
因为你希望攻击者对别人的密码下手。
Just like in the physical world, even though it's a bit uncomfortable to consider, you're The house doesn't need to be 100% secure.
就像现实世界中一样，虽然想起来有点不舒服，但你自己就是。 房子不需要100%安全。
And indeed, it's difficult to make it such.
实际上，也很难做到这一点。
There's always going to be a point of weakness. Maybe it's that window, the door, or something like that.
总会有弱点。 可能是窗户、门或类似的东西。
But if your home is more secure than the next door home, just probabilistically, you are more secure.
但如果你的家比隔壁邻居家更安全，从概率上来说，你就更安全。
You're not secure.
你并不安全。
And indeed, any website you see down the road that says, we are secure because we do x, y, or z, that's nonsense.
事实上，你在路上看到的任何网站，如果它说“因为我们做了 x、y 或 z，所以我们很安全”，那都是胡说八道。
Security is really about comparisons and evaluating things, if quantitatively, relative to some other system, relative to some other code.
安全性实际上是比较和评估事物，如果要量化的话，是相对于其他系统、其他代码而言的。
So what's the takeaway here?
那么，这里的要点是什么呢？
Well, hopefully a non-trivial number of you will go home this weekend on Monday and change at least one passcode.
好吧，希望你们中不少人会在本周末或下周一回家后，至少更改一个密码。
But there's going to be a trade-off here.
但这将是一个权衡。
And we talk about this all the time in CS50.
我们在 CS50 中一直都在讨论这个问题。
Any time we improve something, we pay some price in time, in performance, in cost somewhere else.
每当我们改进某些东西时，我们都要在时间、性能、成本等方面付出代价。
So what's the downside, then, of this advice, that you should use minimally eight-character passcodes?
那么，使用至少八个字符的密码的建议有什么缺点呢？
Why might you want to say nay and not do this?
你为什么可能想说不，不想这么做呢？
Say again? You have to remember it, right?
再说一遍？你必须记住它，对吧？
And so here, there is sort of some sociology.
所以这里面有一些社会学的东西。
There's some human behavior.
有一些人类行为。
Some of you might have colleagues, if you're working in the real world, at least back in healthier times when you had colleagues with desks and cubicles.
你们中的一些人可能有同事，如果你在现实世界中工作，至少在过去更健康的时期，你的同事有办公桌和隔间。
And there's probably one person in the office with a Post-it note on their monitor with their passcode.
办公室里可能会有一个人，他们的显示器上贴着写有密码的便利贴。
It's a bit of a cybersecurity offense.
这有点网络安全犯罪的意味。
But it's also a sort of real-world side effect, maybe, of corporate policies that aren't really calibrated for human behavior.
但这也许也是公司政策没有真正根据人类行为进行调整而造成的一种现实副作用。
So we'll see if there's some other defenses.
我们看看有没有其他防御措施。
And indeed, let me propose that we talk briefly about one that actually tends to kick in automatically.
我们来简单地讨论一个实际上往往会自动启动的防御措施。
Even if your passcode is not as strong as we've just seen, one of these six quadrillion possibilities, well, what could we do instead?
即使你的密码不像我们刚才看到的那么强大，只有这 6 千万亿种可能性中的一种，那我们还能怎么做？
Well, has anyone, and I'll zoom in on this here, accidentally locked themselves out of their own phone before?
这里有人曾经不小心把自己锁在手机外面吗？
Like, when does that happen? Yeah, when you try the password.
什么时候会发生这种情况？当你尝试输入密码的时候。
Yeah, so too many times.
试了太多次。
Maybe your finger is slightly off.
也许你的手指稍微偏了一点。
Maybe you're slightly off.
也许你只是稍微偏了一点。
And you just don't input the same passcode correctly after, like, five times, 10 times.
你在五次、十次之后，都没能正确输入相同的密码。
There's some reasonable threshold.
这里有一个合理的阈值。
And why does that happen?
为什么会发生这种情况？
Well, Apple and Google equivalently figure, just probabilistically, if after 10 guesses you still haven't typed in the right passcode, probably you're not you.
Apple 和 Google 都从概率上认为，如果在 10 次尝试后你仍然没有输入正确的密码，那你很可能不是你自己。
You're someone else who's picked up your phone.
你是捡到手机的其他人。
So we're just going to go ahead and lock you out.
所以我们会把你锁在外面。
Now, what's the effect of this?
这样做有什么效果？
Well, this means now that each of those possible passcodes no longer takes roughly one second.
这意味着现在尝试每种可能的密码不再需要大约一秒钟。
Now it takes roughly one minute.
现在大约需要一分钟。
So the attack is still the same.
攻击方式还是一样的。
But if it's now one passcode or 10 guesses per minute, we have significantly, by a factor of 60 in this story, slowed things down.
但如果现在每分钟只能猜一次密码或有 10 次猜测机会，速度就明显慢下来了，在这个例子中慢了 60 倍。
And unfortunately, does anyone know what happens if you screw up again after a minute?
不幸的是，有人知道如果你在一分钟后再次输入错误会发生什么吗？
Yeah, it goes longer. It's like five minutes, and then 10 minutes.
是的，时间会更长。 可能是 5 分钟，然后是 10 分钟。
And Google is kind of obnoxious about it.
Google 在这方面做得有点讨厌。
They don't even give you a time frame.
他们甚至没有给你一个时间范围。
They just say, try again later.
他们只会说，稍后再试。
And so that keeps not only the adversary out, but also potentially you.
因此，这不仅将攻击者拒之门外，还可能将你自己拒之门外。
So therein lies that trade-off.
这就是权衡利弊所在。
If you've forgotten your code, if nowadays your finger is slightly wet so the screen isn't responding correctly, these could be usability downsides too.
如果你忘记了密码，如果你的手指现在有点湿，导致屏幕反应不灵敏，这些也可能是可用性方面的缺点。
So security is really just about finding the sweet spot among these various trade-offs here.
因此，安全性实际上就是在这些各种权衡之间找到最佳点。
But there's other mechanisms, too.
但还有其他机制。
And some of you might recognize this screen from Gmail, via which, of course, you log in.
你们中的一些人可能从 Gmail 中认出这个屏幕，当然，你是通过它登录的。
But after you log into Gmail or similar websites or apps or systems at work nowadays especially, you might be presented with what's called two-factor authentication.
但是，在你登录 Gmail 或类似的网站、应用程序或工作系统之后，尤其是现在，你可能会看到所谓的双重身份验证。
And what is this in a nutshell, in layperson's terms?
简而言之，用外行人的话说，这是什么？
Many of you, if you do anything digitally at work, might have to do this now, yeah.
如果你们中的许多人在工作中进行任何数字操作，现在可能都必须这样做。
Exactly, you get texted at your phone an additional code that's not your same password.
没错，你会在手机上收到一个额外的代码，这个代码与你的密码不同。
It's typically a numeric code, maybe six digits long.
它通常是一个数字代码，可能有六位数长。
It expires after a minute or 10 minutes.
它在一分钟或十分钟后过期。
But why is this a good thing?
但这为什么是件好事呢？
Well, one, it's no longer just a piece of information that you know or that you might have written down.
首先，它不再仅仅是一条你知道的信息，或者你可能已经写下来的信息。
It's information that changes every time you try to log in.
每次登录都会变化的信息。
But more importantly, it's a fundamentally second factor, which means it's not just something you know.
但更重要的是，它本质上是第二个因素，这意味着它不仅仅是你知道的东西。
Now it's something you have, so you, for instance,
现在它是你拥有的东西，所以你，例如，
are the only one, theoretically, that should be receiving that code.
理论上是唯一应该收到验证码的人。
And so now the adversary, if they want to get into your account, not only have to guess or brute force or maybe read off of a Post-it note your password, they also have to physically have access now to that phone.
因此，如果攻击者想要进入你的帐户，他们不仅要猜测、暴力破解，或者从便利贴上读取你的密码，现在他们还必须物理上接触到你的手机。
So there's still a threat, absolutely.
所以仍然存在威胁，这是肯定的。
But it's not everyone on the internet with an internet connection Now it's only the people in Starbucks.
但它不再是互联网上任何拥有网络连接的人，现在只是星巴克里的人。
Now it's only the people at work.
现在只是工作中的人。
Now it's only the people in your home who might have access to that second factor.
现在只有你家里的人可能接触到第二个因素。
So there, too, it just raises the bar to the adversary, making it harder, more time-consuming, more geographically impossible for them to attack you.
因此，这也提高了攻击者的门槛，使其更难、更耗时、在地理位置上更不可能攻击你。
But what's the downside of two-factor authentication?
但双重身份验证的缺点是什么？
Whether it's a device, or even nowadays, it's in software, whether it's on your keychain or on your phone, where you're prompted for this code.
无论是设备，还是现在软件中，无论是在你的钥匙链上还是手机上，当你被提示输入验证码时。
What's a downside, as some of us have probably experienced, too?
正如我们中的一些人可能经历过的那样，有什么缺点？
You forget your cell phone, absolutely, right?
你忘记带手机了，绝对正确？
The factor that you have, you don't have with you, or maybe you're in a basement somewhere, don't have reception, you're on a plane, you can't get the code.
你所拥有的因素，你却没有带在身边，或者你在某个地下室，没有信号，你在飞机上，你无法获得验证码。
And so there, too, are these trade-offs.
因此，这里也存在这些权衡。
And even IT departments need to keep that in mind, because what does that mean for them?
即使是 IT 部门也需要记住这一点，因为这对他们意味着什么？
Well, if you don't have your phone with you, and you are in the habit of calling IT to help you fix this, now there's a cost, a human cost, maybe even a financial cost.
如果你没有随身携带手机，并且你习惯于打电话给 IT 寻求帮助来解决这个问题，那么现在就有成本，人力成本，甚至可能是财务成本。
And so IT policy nowadays is really just about finding the right balance and where we want to spend our resources, but at least raise the bar to the adversary.
所以现在的 IT 策略实际上就是找到合适的平衡点，以及我们想要在哪里投入资源，但至少要提高攻击者的门槛。
But of course, there's other ways, too.
当然，还有其他方法。
And this is going to be one of our homework assignments, if you will, after today.
这将是今天之后我们其中一项家庭作业。
There's this software called Password Managers.
有一种软件叫密码管理器。
And no need to buzz in on your phone, but maybe with a physical hand, how many folks here use a password?
不用在手机上回答，就用手举起来示意下，有多少人使用密码管理器？
Manager, OK, let me ballpark this at 10%, 20% perhaps.
我估计一下，大概有 10% 到 20%。
OK, so we've got 80% upside here and a lesson learned potentially.
所以我们还有 80% 的增长空间，这可能也是个学习的机会。
So a password manager is just a piece of software on your Mac, your PC, or your phone nowadays that manages your passwords.
密码管理器就是 Mac、PC 或手机上的一种软件，用来管理你的密码。
Well, what does that mean?
这意味着什么呢？
When you go to a website for the first time or you download an app for the first time and you have to create an account,
当你第一次访问某个网站或下载某个应用程序时，需要创建一个帐户，
You can still use your email address or David as your username or whatever your name might be.
你仍然可以使用你的电子邮件地址或 David 作为用户名，或者你的名字。
So you don't have to change that methodology.
所以你不需要改变这种方法。
But instead of typing in 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 as your same password for that website or app as well as for every other, now you use the Password Manager software to generate something difficult to guess for you.
但现在你不必像其他所有网站和应用程序一样，输入 123456 作为密码了，你可以使用密码管理器软件为你生成难以猜测的密码。
That is, you tell the Password Manager,
也就是说，你告诉密码管理器，
Give me an eight-character random passcode, not 0, 0, 0, 0, but something with punctuation, with numbers, with letters.
给我一个 8 个字符的随机密码，不是 0000，而是包含标点符号、数字和字母的密码。
And better yet, the password manager, as the name suggests, remembers that password for you.
顾名思义，密码管理器会为你记住这个密码。
And the next time you go to another website, you do it again with a completely different password, maybe same username, maybe two-factor authentication.
下次你访问其他网站时，可以使用完全不同的密码再次执行此操作，用户名可以相同，也可以使用双重身份验证。
But different password, different password, different password.
但密码不同，每个网站都不一样。
And it doesn't have to be eight.
而且不一定是 8 位。
I mean, I'm in the habit of using a dozen, two dozen characters in total.
我通常使用 12 或 24 个字符。
And at that point, I can't even pronounce the number of possibilities because it goes well beyond the quadrillion.
在这种情况下，我甚至无法说出有多少种可能性，因为它远远超过了 quadrillion。
So the probability that someone's going to get into one of those accounts for me now is very, very, very low.
所以现在别人进入我其中一个帐户的概率非常非常低。
And they're going to take less interest in me and maybe more interest in someone else that's not using as good of a password.
他们对我的兴趣会减少，也许会对那些没有使用那么好的密码的人更感兴趣。
Now, what does this mean in real terms?
那么，这实际上意味着什么呢？
Well, when you go to log into that managed site, you don't manually type your password anymore.
当你登录那个托管网站时，你不再需要手动输入密码了。
In fact, you don't generally even need to know it.
实际上，你通常甚至不需要知道它。
Nowadays, I probably don't know 90-plus, 99% of my passwords.
如今，我可能不知道我 90% 以上，甚至 99% 的密码了。
I entrust them to this password manager.
我把它们托付给了这个密码管理器。
Now, of course, you'd like to think that the password manager itself is secure.
当然，你希望密码管理器本身是安全的。
So what might that mean?
那这意味着什么呢？
Well, those of you who do use a password manager, how do you access that software itself?
那些使用密码管理器的人，你们是如何访问这个软件本身的呢？
What's protecting your data?
是什么保护着你的数据？
In your understanding.
根据你的理解。
So maybe biometrics, like your face ID, or maybe your fingerprint, or maybe more simply, what else?
也许是生物识别技术，比如你的面部识别码，或者你的指纹，或者更简单的，还有什么？
Maybe just a password.
也许只是一个密码。
And hopefully, that password, that primary password, that gatekeeper, is not itself 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
希望那个密码，那个主密码，那个守门人，本身不是 123456。
Otherwise, it doesn't matter how secure all of the others are.
否则，其他密码的安全程度就无关紧要了。
But if you're willing to put in the effort and pick one pretty long,
但如果你愿意付出努力，选择一个相当长的，
Somewhat random, very unguessable password that you just promise to commit to memory.
有点随机，非常难以猜测的密码，你保证记住它。
And maybe for backup, you literally print it out and put it in a safe deposit box or a safe or just kind of hide it somewhere physically that there's very low probability someone's going to find the backup copy.
为了备份，你可以把它打印出来，放在保险箱里，或者藏在别人很难找到的地方。
That might be a loan.
那可能是个办法。
But of course, the flip side is now, if you forget that primary password, you've now lost all of the eggs in the basket.
但另一方面，如果你忘记了主密码，你就失去了所有的一切。
If someone gets that primary password, now they have access to everything.
如果有人获取了你的主密码，他们就能访问你所有的信息。
So that's rather the trade-off.
这就是取舍。
But I dare say you're probably less threatened, depending on your family, by the people immediately around you than the billions of other people on the internet that have access, potentially, to those same systems.
但我敢说，你身边的人对你造成的威胁，可能比互联网上数十亿有途径访问这些系统的人要小，这取决于你的家庭情况。
So there, too, it's a trade-off.
这也是一种取舍。
And it's up to you to decide whether or not to manage your passwords in this way.
是否以这种方式管理密码，由你自己决定。
But if you were on that top 10 list, or even if you're not, but you can think of several accounts that all have the same password, you're probably going to benefit from something like this.
但如果你榜上有名，或者即使你没有，但你能想到好几个账号都使用了相同的密码，你很可能会从密码管理器中受益。
And why is it bad, to be clear, to use the same password on multiple sites, in case that's never sort of dawned in thought?
如果这个问题你从未想过，那我来明确地解释下，为什么在多个网站上使用相同的密码是不好的？
Why is that a bad thing, to reuse a password on different websites, different apps?
在不同的网站、不同的应用程序上重复使用密码，为什么不好？
Any intuition? Yeah, in back?
有什么想法吗？后面的同学？
Exactly, once it's attacked, the adversary, presumably by transitivity, can see, oh, well, if this user's username is malan at harvard.edu on this website, and their password is foolishly 123456, or even something way more complicated,
没错，一旦某个账户被攻击，攻击者很可能会顺藤摸瓜，
发现如果这个用户的用户名在这个网站上是 malan at harvard.edu，而他们的密码是愚蠢的 123456，或者更复杂的东西，
they can probably just assume with high probability that if I'm being a little reckless, let's try accessing malan at harvard.edu's other accounts, other apps, using that exact same password.
他们很可能会假设，如果我再大胆一点，用完全相同的密码，尝试访问 malan at harvard.edu 的其他账户和其他应用程序。
And so by transitivity, essentially, you're putting your other accounts at risk.
因此，从本质上讲，你是在将你的其他账户置于风险之中。
So what's maybe a takeaway minimally here?
那么，我们至少可以从中得到什么启示？
I would start to reconsider your passcodes on your most important data.
我建议你重新审视一下你最重要的数据的密码。
Maybe it's medical. Maybe it's financial. Maybe it's email. Anything remotely personal that you really wouldn't want to have access.
也许是医疗信息，也许是财务信息，也许是电子邮件。任何你真的不想被别人访问的个人信息。
Do you necessarily need the same level of security on e-commerce?
电子商务网站是否需要同等级别的安全保障？
Commerce sites or sites that you don't really care about or that you signed up for once and after that, eh, that's it?
那些你不太关心，或者你注册过一次之后就不再使用的购物网站呢？
Probably not.
可能不需要。
So you can decide for yourself.
你自己决定。
But again, software, like a password manager, and these are just some of the possibilities out there, are probably to be your friend.
但是，像密码管理器这样的软件，这只是一些可行的方案，可能会成为你的朋友。
A couple of these are free.
其中一些是免费的。
They come with Windows or Mac OS.
它们随 Windows 或 Mac OS 系统附带。
A couple are commercial.
有一些是商业软件。
Harvard has a site license for students for one of these as well.
哈佛大学也为学生提供了其中一种软件的网站许可证。
So there are options out there.
所以市面上有很多选择。
But what else do people use?
但是人们还用什么呢？
What else can people use to keep their system secure?
人们还可以用什么来确保系统的安全？
So most of us nowadays.
现如今我们大多数人
have probably heard of encryption, this technique for just kind of scrambling information.
可能都听说过加密，这种扰乱信息的加密技术。
So when you want to send a message, an email, or upload a photograph, or use your credit card, hopefully it's not just being sent out for all to see, but there's some kind of scrambling going on.
当你想要发送信息、电子邮件、上传照片或使用信用卡时，它不会被公开，而是经过某种方式加密。
And some fancy mathematics ensure that encryption ensures that only you, the sender, And someone else, the receiver, can theoretically see what that credit card number is, what that message is, what that photograph is instead.
一些高级的数学算法确保了加密，确保只有你（发送方）和接收方才能看到信用卡号码、信息内容、照片内容。
So encryption is sort of commonplace nowadays, both in websites and apps and ATMs and other such devices.
所以加密在今天很常见，无论是在网站、应用程序、ATM 机还是其他设备中。
But how does it work?
但它是如何工作的？
Well, back in week two of CS50, your child learned a little something about encryption, otherwise known as cryptography.
在 CS50 的第二周，你的孩子学习了一些关于加密的知识，也称为密码学。
And one of the algorithms we talked about was quite simply something like this.
我们讨论过的一种算法非常简单，就像这样。
This is what we might call, not only CS50, but plain text.
这不仅是 CS50，我们也可以称之为明文。
So very plain text that, in this case, is English.
在这种情况下，是非常简单的英文文本。
And obviously, everyone in the room can read it.
显然，房间里的每个人都能读懂它。
But what if I wanted to send this message out to someone in this room or out on the internet, or maybe equivalently back in the day, maybe write a message down on a scrap of paper in grade school and pass a secret note, a secret love note, to someone in class with hopes that the teacher or any other students in the class can't intercept it and read it?
但是如果我想把这条信息发送给房间里的某个人，或者发送到互联网上，
或者像过去那样，写在纸条上传递，希望老师或班上的其他同学无法拦截和阅读它，那该怎么办？
Well, you probably don't want to say, this is CS50, or I love you, or anything remotely sensitive.
你可能不会想说“这是 CS50”或“我爱你”，或任何稍微敏感的内容。
But rather, maybe you want to encrypt it.
而是想加密它。
And let's change the T to a U. Maybe change the H to an I, the I to a J, the S to a T, the I to a J, the S to a T again, the C to a D, the S to a T. And we'll just leave the numbers alone, even though I worry someone could probably guess what this now does say nonetheless.
把 T 变成 U，H 变成 I，I 变成 J，S 变成 T，I 变成 J，
S 再变成 T，C 变成 D，S 变成 T。我们不动数字，虽然我担心有人可能猜到这是什么意思。
But what was the algorithm?
但算法是什么？
as I rattled those changes off, whether student from week two or parents from week now.
我快速地说出这些变化时，无论是第二周的学生还是现在的家长。
Yeah. Just a one-letter shift.
没错，只是字母移位。
And this is more sophisticatedly called a rotational cipher or a Caesar cipher.
这更专业的叫法是旋转密码或凯撒密码。
After Caesar, back in the day, it's relatively simplistic.
以凯撒命名，在过去，它相对简单。
But back in the day, it's not so simplistic if you're the first person in the world to ever use it or think of it.
但在过去，如果你是世界上第一个使用它或想到它的人，它就不那么简单了。
But nowadays, this is not actually what we use.
但现在，我们实际上并不使用它。
But it's similarly mathematical in nature.
但它在本质上同样是数学的。
It's not quite as simple as just adding one or subtracting one to go from now what we'd call ciphertext to plain text.
它不像从现在我们所说的密文到明文那样简单地加一或减一。
But it's similarly math that's involved.
但它同样涉及数学。
And let me just stipulate that the way the math works is that,
让我声明一下，数学的运作方式是，
The sender and the receiver just have to have in mind some kind of secret.
发送方和接收方只需要记住某种秘密。
And the secret in this case would very trivially be 1.
在这种情况下，秘密就是 1。
But it could be a much bigger, much more unguessable number, or maybe some other secret we share, the presumption being that my classmates, my teacher in that grade school classroom,
但它可能是一个更大的、更难猜到的数字，或者是我们共享的其他秘密，前提是我的同学、我在小学课堂上的老师，
if they don't know what that secret is, that number is, yeah, they could try to brute force it and try all possible mathematics, plus 1, plus 2, plus 3.
如果他们不知道这个秘密是什么，不知道这个数字是什么，他们可以尝试暴力破解，尝试所有可能的数学运算，+ 1、+ 2、+ 3。
But that's going to take them some time.
但这需要一些时间。
And they probably don't care enough.
而且他们可能没那么在意。
And so my data might be, and therefore, relatively secure.
因此，我的数据可能相对安全。
But we use encryption all the time nowadays.
但现在加密无处不在。
And so for instance, this is at the start of most URLs nowadays, even if you don't type it yourself.
例如，现在大多数 URL 的开头都是这样的，即使你自己没有输入。
With that said, Safari and even Chrome now are kind of simplifying, if not dumbing down, user interfaces to just hide details that you and I, as sort of normal users, don't need to see 24-7.
话虽如此，Safari 甚至 Chrome 现在都在简化（或者说是弱化）用户界面，隐藏了像你我这样的普通用户不需要整天看到的细节。
But it is there. And if, in fact, on your phone or laptop, you click on the URL, even if it's super short initially, you'll probably see the whole thing.
但它确实存在。实际上，如果你在手机或笔记本电脑上点击 URL，即使它最初很短，你可能也会看到完整的 URL。
Starting with this. And the S means secure.
以这个开头。 S 代表安全。
The S means that encryption's being used.
S 表示正在使用加密。
But there's other forms of this, not just when you visit websites.
但这还有其他形式，不仅仅是在你访问网站的时候。
There's this, end-to-end encryption, which is being talked about more nowadays, especially during COVID times, with so many more of us on video and
现在越来越多的人谈论端到端加密，特别是在新冠疫情期间，我们中有更多的人在使用视频，
talking about more sensitive things, telemedicine, talking to doctors, things that you also wouldn't want to verbally or visually get out into the wild, just like text.
谈论更敏感的事情，比如远程医疗，与医生交谈，这些事情你也不希望像文字一样被泄露出去。
What's different about end-to-end encryption versus HTTPS and the type of encryption that most of us use every day on websites alone?
端到端加密与 HTTPS 以及我们大多数人每天在网站上使用的加密类型有什么不同？
End-to-end encryption is sort of a better feature that you want to increasingly seek when using services like Zoom or Microsoft Teams or WhatsApp or the like.
端到端加密是一种更好的功能，在使用 Zoom、Microsoft Teams、WhatsApp 等服务时，你应该越来越多地寻求这种功能。
Any instincts here?
有什么想法吗？
Yeah, over on the right.
是的，右边那位。
Good, so the encryption, the scrambling of information happens in the source, the sender, and the destination, the receiver, without a so-called middleman in between.
很好，所以加密，也就是信息的 scrambling，发生在信息的来源（发送方）和目的地（接收方），中间没有所谓的中间人。
And this is actually very different from most contexts nowadays that use just HTTPS, because when you're using HTTPS to buy something on Amazon securely with your credit card, well, of course, Amazon needs to be able to decrypt the message at the end of the day.
这实际上与现在大多数只使用 HTTPS 的情况非常不同，因为当你使用 HTTPS 在 Amazon 上用信用卡安全地购物时，Amazon 最终需要解密信息。
And so that's fine.
所以这没问题。
But even when you're using services like video conferencing or maybe Text messaging nowadays.
但即使在你使用视频会议或现在的短信服务时也是如此。
Well, if you're using WhatsApp, that's owned by Meta.
如果你使用 WhatsApp，它属于 Meta 公司。
And if you're using Instagram, that's owned by Meta.
如果你使用 Instagram，它也属于 Meta 公司。
There's a lot of middlemen in these apps that we're using.
在我们使用的这些应用程序中，有很多中间人。
And if they were only using encryption, period, or only using something like HTTPS, yes, your connection from you to WhatsApp And in turn, to the recipient, might very well be secure on each end of that channel.
如果他们只使用加密，或者只使用类似HTTPS的东西，那么你与WhatsApp的连接，以及反过来，与接收者的连接，在通道的两端很可能是安全的。
But meta, in between the company and any other company in between, could theoretically, for better or for worse, be looking at that data, whether it's to mine it for advertising purposes, whether it's to snoop on data that you're sending.
但是 Meta，作为中间的公司，或者任何其他的中间公司，
理论上，无论好坏，都可以查看这些数据，无论是为了广告目的而挖掘数据，还是为了窥探你发送的数据。
That is not end-to-end encryption if the middleman, a company typically, has technically access to that data.
如果中间人（通常是公司）在技术上能够访问这些数据，那就不是端到端加密。
Now, Zoom and Microsoft Teams and WhatsApp and iMessage and other services with which you're familiar increasingly are offering stronger guarantees of encryption, whereby it's indeed between parties A and B and not the one in the middle.
现在，Zoom、Microsoft Teams、WhatsApp、iMessage 以及你熟悉的其他服务，越来越多地提供更强大的加密保证，确保数据只在通信双方之间传递，而不是中间人。
Now, there's downsides here. And you can actually see this kind of functionality manifest in certain settings.
当然，这也有缺点。你可以在某些设置中看到这种功能的表现形式。
For instance, besides iMessage, Which just does this for you on iPhones or Macs.
例如，除了 iMessage，它只在 iPhone 或 Mac 上为你提供这种功能。
Besides Zoom, you can actually fine-tune these settings, indeed, within Zoom itself.
除了 Zoom，你实际上可以在 Zoom 中微调这些设置。
So here's a screenshot that I took last night of just what the user interface looks like today to create a new Zoom meeting with the latest version of Zoom software.
这是我昨晚截取的屏幕截图，展示了使用最新版 Zoom 软件创建新会议时的用户界面。
And maybe unbeknownst to you, there's a choice of buttons down here
你可能不知道，这里可以选择按钮。
And most likely, yours is by default on enhanced encryption, which is brilliant marketing speak, because it's just encryption.
默认情况下，你的按钮很可能是“增强加密”，这是一个很棒的营销话术，因为它只是加密。
It's not enhanced.
它并没有增强。
It actually, ironically, means worse than this.
讽刺的是，它实际上比这更糟糕。
But they want you using it, most likely.
但他们很可能希望你使用它。
Why?
为什么？
Well, it's a little easier to implement.
因为它更容易实现。
It's a little less expensive for them computationally.
他们在计算上的成本更低。
And to be fair, enhanced encryption does scramble the data, But not in a way that Zoom can't see it.
公平地说，增强加密确实会对数据进行加密，但 Zoom 仍然可以看到它。
Zoom can indeed see it, but that's actually a plus in some contexts.
Zoom 确实可以看到它，但这在某些情况下实际上是一个优势。
Because if you want to do cloud recordings and you want a meeting recorded not on your Mac or PC, but let Zoom deal with that.
因为如果你想进行云录制，并且想将会议录制到 Zoom 上而不是你的 Mac 或 PC 上。
If you want automatic transcription nowadays, so the words to appear, whether it's English or something else on the screen, well, you can't really lock Zoom or any other middleman out of that because someone needs to save it to the cloud.
如果你想要自动转录，无论是英语还是屏幕上的其他语言，你都不能真正阻止 Zoom 或任何其他中间人访问，因为需要有人将它保存到云端。
Someone needs to translate the voice to those English or some other language words.
需要有人将语音翻译成英语或其他语言的文字。
So enhanced encryption enables those features, but they also allow a bad actor, malicious employee, someone who's just nosy at Zoom or the equivalent middleman to just kind of poke around your video conference and hear what you've said or see what you've typed as well, unless you instead check
增强型加密功能支持这些功能，但它们也允许不法分子、恶意员工、Zoom
或类似中间商的好事者窥探你的视频会议，听到你说的话或看到你输入的内容，
this box as well. So increasingly, look for mentions of end-to-end encryption, or give that some thought when you choose a technology via which to communicate with someone, whether it's within your family or without as well.
除非你勾选这个框。当你选择一种技术与他人交流时，无论是与家人还是其他人交流，都要越来越多地关注端到端加密的字样，或者认真考虑这一点。
Now, last but not least, there's other applications of encryption, too.
最后但同样重要的是，加密还有其他应用。
And this, too, might be a lesson learned as well.
这可能也是一个教训。
Full disk encryption.
全磁盘加密。
So a disk is like where your data is stored in your Mac or PC or even your phone.
磁盘就像你的数据存储在 Mac、PC 甚至手机上的地方。
And full disk encryption just means, ideally, that all of your data is encrypted, that is, somehow scrambled.
全磁盘加密意味着，理想情况下，你所有的数据都被加密了，也就是说，以某种方式被加密了。
Now, hopefully, your password for your computer or phone is good enough that
现在，希望你的电脑或手机密码足够安全
Even though the device is encrypted with that password, at least you'll remember it, and your phone or your Mac or PC will automatically decrypt it for you.
即使设备是用该密码加密的，至少你还能记住它，而且你的手机、Mac 或 PC 会自动为你解密。
Of course, you can't scramble the information and hide it from ourselves.
当然，我们不能把信息加密起来，然后对我们自己隐藏起来。
One of us, at least, for these devices needs to have access.
对于这些设备，我们中至少有一个人需要有访问权限。
But full disk encryption typically means that at least when you close the laptop lid or power down for the night, that even if someone else steals that device, opens the lid, unless they have your passcode,
但全磁盘加密通常意味着，至少当你合上笔记本电脑盖或在晚上关机时，即使其他人偷走了你的设备，打开了盖子，除非他们有你的密码，
They can't even plug in fancy cables to the device and just rip the 0's and 1's off of the device and see what's actually there.
他们甚至无法将花哨的电缆插入设备，然后直接从设备上获取 0 和 1，查看实际内容。
Full disk encryption means they could do that, but they would just see seemingly random 0's and 1's.
全磁盘加密意味着他们可以这样做，但他们只会看到看似随机的 0 和 1。
Now, there's a downside here, too. This might slow things down potentially, but it is a feature increasingly that's offered, and it's absolutely something you should consider enabling in general, especially if your laptop or phone travels with you, and certainly your phone does.
当然，这也有缺点。这可能会降低速度，但它是一个越来越普遍的功能，
你绝对应该考虑启用它，特别是如果你的笔记本电脑或手机随身携带，当然你的手机也是如此。
Or if you plan to donate or sell or give away a device, you don't want to leave all of the zeros and ones, the remnants of your own sensitive data, passed on there.
或者，如果你打算捐赠、出售或赠送设备，你不希望将所有零和一，即你自己敏感数据的残余部分，传递出去。
So Windows has a feature called BitLocker.
Windows 有一个名为 BitLocker 的功能。
Mac OS has a feature called FileVault.
Mac OS 有一个名为 FileVault 的功能。
There's commercial options as well.
也有商业选项。
But generally, we're at the point now in 2022 where clicking a button is sufficient to enable these features.
通常情况下，在 2022 年的今天，点击一个按钮就足以启用这些功能。
With that said, don't rush into all of these decisions.
话虽如此，不要急于做所有这些决定。
I would make backups of your data.
我会备份你的数据。
And don't maybe email CS50 if something goes wrong with that process.
如果过程中出现问题，不要给 CS50 发邮件。
But I would do your own due diligence.
但我会做自己的尽职调查。
But this, too, would be a menu of possibilities.
但这也是一种可能性。
And now the bad side, the downside of what seems to be great, this notion of full disk encryption.
现在说说全盘加密这个看似很好的概念的坏处和不足之处。
Unfortunately, just as we can encrypt our data to protect it from the adversaries, so can the adversaries, if they get into our devices, encrypt our data and do what?
不幸的是，正如我们可以加密数据以保护其免遭攻击者攻击一样，攻击者如果进入我们的设备，也可以加密我们的数据并做什么？
Not tell us that secret key.
不告诉我们密钥。
And so this is generally applied in the context of ransomware, which, tragically, you increasingly hear about in hospital systems, school systems, municipalities, where systems are getting attacked.
这种情况通常出现在勒索软件的背景下，不幸的是，你越来越多地在医院系统、学校系统、市政当局听到系统遭到攻击的事件。
And the data is not just getting stolen, because what does the adversary typically need with local, municipal, or even hospital data?
数据不仅仅是被盗，因为攻击者通常需要本地、市政甚至医院的数据做什么？
The value to the adversary is encrypting All of the hospital, all of the municipality's data, preventing them from accessing it if they have no backups or the like.
对攻击者来说，价值在于加密医院、市政当局的所有数据，如果他们没有备份或类似的东西，就阻止他们访问这些数据。
And so ransomware is literally about trying to convince someone to pay you money or pay you Bitcoin or something like that to give you that secret key.
所以勒索软件实际上是想说服某人付钱给你，或者付给你比特币之类的东西，来换取密钥。
And this key, in this case, is surely more sophisticated than the number one.
在这种情况下，这个密钥肯定比数字 1 复杂得多。
But it's really the same idea.
但实际上是同一个道理。
So here, too, yet again, a trade-off.
这里又是一个权衡。
Just as we sort of invent something for good, it can also be used for evil, so to speak, as well.
正如我们发明东西是为了做好事一样，它也可以被用来做坏事。
But it's really the same underlying principles, even though we keep seeing it and hearing about it in these different forms.
但这其实是同一个基本原理，即使我们不断地在不同的形式中看到它和听到它。
And lastly, if only because folks are generally familiar but don't necessarily know what it is that it's doing for them,
最后，仅仅因为人们通常都很熟悉，但不一定知道它在为他们做什么，
browsers nowadays have what's often called incognito mode or private mode, which has nothing to do with encryption but does have to do with cybersecurity or really cyber privacy, keeping your data from prying eyes.
现在的浏览器有一种通常被称为隐身模式或隐私模式的功能，这与加密无关，但与网络安全或网络隐私有关，可以保护你的数据不被窥探。
Incognito mode, if you open it in Chrome, for instance, looks a little something like this.
例如，在 Chrome 中打开隐身模式，看起来是这样的。
And we use it in CS50 when introducing students, as we did last week, to web programming,
在 CS50 这门课上，我们会在介绍学生进行网页编程时使用它，就像我们上周做的那样，
because it, in effect, lets you start with a clean slate, like a brand new browser that has never visited any websites before, which is good for just diagnosing problems.
因为它实际上可以让你从头开始，就像一个从未访问过任何网站的全新浏览器一样，这对诊断问题很有帮助。
But it's often commonly used if you want to log into maybe your Gmail account on someone else's computer and you don't want your password being saved, or you want to visit some website where you don't want the URL or the search terms ending up in your autocomplete history.
如果你想在别人的电脑上登录你的 Gmail 帐户，又不想保存密码，
或者你想访问某个网站，但不想让网址或搜索词出现在自动完成历史记录中，那么它也经常被用到。
So there's multiple uses for incognito mode.
所以隐身模式有很多用途。
But what does it really do?
但它到底有什么作用呢？
Well, it doesn't stop your company.
它并不能阻止你的公司。
It doesn't stop your university, your internet service provider, be it Comcast, Verizon, or the like, from knowing what websites you go to.
它也无法阻止你的大学、你的互联网服务提供商（无论是 Comcast、Verizon 还是类似的公司）知道你访问了哪些网站。
Because ask your students.
问问你的学生就知道了。
A couple of weeks ago, we talked about, actually a week ago, we talked about how the internet works.
几周前，实际上是上周，我们讨论了互联网的工作原理。
And unfortunately, every computer has an IP address, which is unique identifier, which goes out anytime you go anywhere, incognito mode or not.
不幸的是，每台计算机都有一个 IP 地址，它是一个唯一的标识符，无论你什么时候去哪里，无论是否使用隐身模式，它都会被发送出去。
So this isn't really covering your tracks outside of your office, or outside of your home, or outside of your company.
因此，这并不能真正地掩盖你在办公室、家庭或公司之外的踪迹。
But it is at least throwing away local information.
但它至少会丢弃本地信息。
And so we'll talk, in fact, in CS50's week 9 this coming Monday about cookies, which you might generally know about, and what are called sessions.
我们将在下周一 CS50 的第 9 周讨论 Cookie（你可能已经有所了解）以及 Session。
And so long story short, what incognito mode does is it throws away, when you close the window, any locally stored information to these things called cookies.
简而言之，隐身模式的作用是，当你关闭窗口时，它会丢弃存储在 Cookie 中的所有本地信息。
Which are sort of like virtual hand stamps that just remember what you've logged in as or what's in your shopping cart or the like.
Cookie 就像虚拟的印章，它会记住你登录的帐户、购物车里的商品等等。
But it doesn't hide any information from anyone outside of your own Mac or PC.
但它不会向你自己的 Mac 或 PC 以外的任何人隐藏任何信息。
It only prevents those local prying eyes.
它只能防止那些本地窥探者的窥视。
So there too, even though we have tools that many of you are probably in the habit of using or thinking you should use to be more private, be more secure on the internet, what we do really in CS50, both weeks past and future, is talk about.
因此，即使我们有许多人可能习惯使用或认为应该使用的工具来在互联网上获得更高的隐私和安全，
我们在 CS50 课程中，无论是过去几周还是未来几周，真正要做的是讨论。
how these technologies work so that ultimately we have all the more of an educated citizenry here among undergrads and here as well as online so that you can apply these same lessons learned to problems you'll encounter in the future.
这些技术是如何工作的，以便最终我们能在这里的本科生和在线学生中
培养出更多受过教育的公民，让你们能够将学到的这些经验教训应用到未来遇到的问题中。
So as promised, the homework. One should probably use a password manager.
如前所述，作业应该使用密码管理器。
It doesn't have to be one of those ones on the list, but at least starting that conversation maybe with someone who does, maybe it's often
不一定非要局限于列表中的这些人，但至少可以和这些人开始聊一聊，
The students in your family, perhaps, who can advise you on some of these technologies, consider using a password manager, too.
也许通常是你家里懂技术的学生，也许可以给你一些建议，也可以考虑使用密码管理器。
Using two-factor authentication, whether it's your phone or some key fob or the like, but at least seeking out that feature, at least for accounts that you really care about.
使用双重身份验证，无论是手机、密钥卡还是其他类似的东西，但至少要启用该功能，至少在你真正关心的帐户上要启用。
Your email, social media, financial, medical, anything where you'd be embarrassed at best or really violated at worst if that kind of information got out.
比如你的电子邮件、社交媒体、财务、医疗，任何一旦泄露就会让你尴尬甚至更糟糕的事情。
And then increasingly using not just encryption, which you kind of get automatically from most technologies today, but increasingly choosing technologies that offer stronger guarantees t
然后越来越多地使用不仅仅是加密技术（现在大多数技术都能自动实现），而是选择那些提供更强保证的技术，
that keep those middlemen, those companies, out of the way, if only so that you can trust with higher probability that only party B knows what party A has said or sent.
将中间人，也就是那些公司排除在外，这样你就可以更有把握地相信只有接收方知道发送方说了什么或发送了什么。
Now, this, of course, was a whirlwind tour.
当然，这只是走马观花。
There's so much more that you can do online.
你可以在网上做的事情还有很多。
Indeed, this course, CS50, can be taken for free online via platforms like edX at edx.org slash CS50.
事实上，这门课程 CS50 可以通过 edX 平台免费在线学习，网址是 edx.org/cs50。
I thought it might be appropriate to end on this note.
我觉得以这句话结尾比较合适。
If anyone would like to conjecture before we start playing music and adjourn for lunch what our final message here is,
在我们开始播放音乐，午餐休息之前，有没有人想猜一猜，我们最后的结束语是什么？
If we reverse the plus 1 and maybe start minus 1 here, minus 1 here.
如果我们把加 1 反过来，从减 1 开始，这里也减 1。
And indeed, thank you so much for coming.
非常感谢大家的到来。
This was CS50.
这就是 CS50。